{
  "reference_number": "12924",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "A target is good (Cf Predator Free NZ target), but whether 0 Mt CO2e or 25 Mt CO2e should be set I'm not sure. The target should be\n ambitious, clear, and science-based.. The target should comply with the Paris Agreement of well below 2 degrees Celsius and striving\n for not more than a 1.5 increase in global temperature. Already at 1.2 degrees the weather extremes, etc being experienced now by\n\n multiple communities and natural systems around the world are too hard to bear... Cross-party consensus should be used to set\n directions/ parameters and the overall target so as to promote political accountability and clarity. The Climate Commission should\n advise on specific targets, adjustments if required - as part of its independent and expert role in advising, monitoring and - widely and\n\n publicly reporting. There needs to be constant education of the public to keep all sorts of environmental issues at the forefront of\n thinking and living in NZ/ Aotearoa."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "While long-lived gases are the big bogeys for climate change, reducing short-lived gases to as low as possible should also be a goal.\n 'Stabilising' levels should be a prelude to going as low as we can. The special place of agriculture in NZ - and methane in particular - is\n recognised, but changes in agriculture would/ should also include changes in land use and kinds and numbers of animals farmed,\n\n perhaps even on a regional/ soil type basis. In particular, there needs to be tighter controls on and monitoring of dairying in many\n parts of NZ. NOTE; Increasing numbers of farmers are becoming more environmentally aware and shifting to 'organic'/ other low-\n\n environmental-impact/ highly sustainable systems. Some of the economic modelling documents produced to provide guidance for\n the zero carbon debate and analysis do not seem to mention this shift and the overall impact it will / could have !!!"
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "To include international emissions/ C units would weaken/ dilute/ confuse NZ's policies and efforts. Inclusion of overseas C credits in\n the past was a fiasco... We need to do what is right here at home. If purchasing of international credits could help some smaller\n\n countries/ more vulnerable areas achieve their zero C goals, NZ could help them in other ways by having an environmentally and\n economically sustainable aid/ development policy."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "BUT - reduced targets only in very special circumstances such as another huge earthquake....and conversely more ambitious targets\n\n - e.g. negative C - if there is a major technological/ practical breakthrough... Targets per se should not allow agriculture and transport\n etc, to drag the chain on moving to a Carbon Zero future. Advising and monitoring by the Climate Change Commission must include\n ALL major sectors and their major stakeholders."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "In general, budgets should be honoured and that is why cross-party consensus is important. The special circumstances clause could\n\nallow for some flexibility, if really needed."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I think questions around second and third budgets is ridiculous. Has it not already been covered above?? Perhaps we should be\nasking more about the length of the Parliamentary Term?"
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Given the 3 year Parliamentary term, perhaps 100 days / 6 months max should be the limit ."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Things to consider • scientific knowledge about climate change • technology relevant to climate change • economic circumstances\n\nand, in particular, the likely impact of the decision on the economy and the competitiveness of particular sectors of the economy •\nfiscal circumstances and, in particular, the likely impact of the decision on taxation, public spending and public borrowing • social\n\ncircumstances and, in particular, the likely impact of the decision on fuel poverty • energy policy and, in particular, the likely impact of\nthe decision on energy supplies and the carbon and energy intensity of the economy • the government’s obligations under the\nTreaty of Waitangi • the three government objectives for climate change policy: sustainable economy, global and local leadership and\n\ncreating a just and inclusive society All major sectors and businesses and representatives of a wide range of stakeholder groups\nshould be included. Public submissions should be kept open and responsive."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "However: Given the important role of the primary sector in the C story, I would hope that representation of agriculture, forestry and\nhorticulture practitioners/ producer organisations, scientists/ innovators and businesses would be increased. Also, what about public\n\nhealth issues and/ or outcomes? Perhaps the Commission would bring in/ consult with different experts according to what was being\ndiscussed - without losing sight of the overall goals and framework of the Act, and keeping within its budgets and targets."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "At least in an overall/ overseeing position."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Advisory role is probably the most important for the Commissioners per se. Perhaps separate agents within the MfE/ agencies such\nas Territorial Authorities should be involved in and tasked with practical mitigation in areas related to adapting to climate change."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "If harvested wood products were better accounted for/ retained within NZ for C credit/ ETS purposes, we could probably achieve\n\nZero C faster and move to more sustainable forestry systems and reduce our almost total dependence on plantation forestry (less\nlogs exported more wood for domestic purposes, etc). New models in the forestry sector are certainly needed. The One Billion Trees\n\nplan is really helpful only if it avoids the pitfalls of past large forestry programmes and includes a better mix of species for avoidance of\nrecent disasters such as in Tolaga Bay... Please keep the environment and environmental impacts right, left and centre in the Zero\nCarbon Bill.. It is encouraging to see some of NZ's biggest companies joining the Zero Carbon movement. They would not do that if it\n\ndid not make economic sense, i.e. be good for their profitability and sustainability....\n\n\n\n\n You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
